# ARGHYA CHATTERJEE

+1-850-450-3804

8

https://citations?user=pg2WMIYAAAAJ

□ arghyachatterjeejohny@gmail.com

 $\bigoplus$ 

https://arghvachatterjee.github.io

https://www.youtube.com/c/ArghyaChatterjeeJony

https://github.com/ArghyaChatterjee

A Robotics, Artificial Intelligence (AI), and Machine Learning (ML) researcher experienced in developing Deep Learning (DL) Algorithms in Computer Vision for Object Detection & Pose Estimation for object Localization and Manipulation with Humanoid Robots in perceptually degraded environments, Advanced Perception Sensor based SLAM for Robot Localization, Mapping, Metric & Semantic understanding of the environment, Risk-aware traversability assessment for autonomous robotic exploration and Swarm Intelligence for multi-robot collaboration & rapid exploration in challenging condition to help take better decision for humans both on earth and on extraterrestrial surfaces like Moon and Mars.

#### **EDUCATION**

• University of West Florida, Florida, USA

Degree: PhD. in Intelligent Systems and Robotics (ISR)

Aug 2022 - Present

CGPA: 3.85/4.00

• Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Degree: BSc. in Mechanical Engineering Feb 2015 - Sept 2019

CGPA: 3.14/4.00

• Khulna Public College, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: HSC in Science Jul 2012 - Aug 2014 GPA: 5.00/5.00 Jul 2012 - Aug 2014  $Class Position: 1^{st}/60$ 

• Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: SSC in Science Jan 2010 - May 2012 GPA: 5.00/5.00 Class Position: 1 st /60

## RESEARCH & PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Visiting Student Researcher, NASA JPL

DARPA organized RACER Program
Perception Team Leader: Dr. Shehryar Khattak (NASA JPL)

May 2023 – Present

California, USA

Topic: Developing novel computer vision algorithms for providing robust autonomy in Polaris Range Rovers of DARPA as part of DARPA RACER (Robotic Autonomy in Complex Environments with Resiliency) program designed specifically for off road navigation in challenging conditions. For Planetary Surface Exploration to Terrestrial Agile Autonomous Robots for Complex terrain Navigation on places like Moon & Mars, the rovers need to deliver critical supplies to astronauts using Lunar Transport Vehicles (LTVs) requiring the intelligence to navigate in dangerous and complex environments with resiliency, agility, and without human intervention.

• Graduate Research Assistant, IHMC (& ISR Lab)

PhD. Thesis in Humanoid Perception (IHMC's Nadia & NASA JSC's Valkyrie) Aug 2022 – Present Project Investigator: Dr. Robert Griffin & Dr. Hakki Erhan Sevil Florida, USA Topic: NeRFs for 3D rendering, volumetric representation, and mesh generation of objects and surroundings in order to detect object & estimate pose for manipulation, to localize & map the environment in a combination of metric and semantic fashion and to assess traversability in the challenging condition for safe navigation with humanoids and legged robots.

Advisor & Robotics Engineer, Lotus Robotics

Research Engineer for ROS based Autonomous Robotics Projects

Oct 2021 – June 2022

Project Coordinator: Mansurul Haque

Newyork, USA

Topic: Developed Autonomous UGVs for GPS guided delivery missions, Autonomous UGVs for Warehouse Security, Lawn Mowing & Floor Scrubbing and Built Autonomous UAVs for agriculture & surveying.

Team Member, Team CoSTAR of NASA JPL

DARPA organized SubT Challenge Perception Team Leader: Dr. Benjamin Morrell (NASA IPL) Jul 2020 – Jan 2022 California, USA Topic: Advanced perception based multi-robot SLAM algorithms efficiency, accuracy & robustness testing along with object detection & localization capability analysis for robots like Spot, Husky & Roller-copter with NeBula autonomy setup (built by Team CoSTAR) mounted.

• Team Supervisor & Educator, STEMX 365

JAXA (& NASA) org. Kibo-Astrobee ISS Robot Programming Challenge
International Project Coordinator: Mizanul H. Chowdhury (MIT)
Tokyo, Japan
Topic: Autonomously operate Astrobee (A free flying robot) inside ISS avoiding obstacles with 3D perception, following way points and detecting OR & AR Tag.

• Software Team Leader & Member, Team Interplanetar

ESA organized ERC & Mars Society organized URC

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Ashiqur Rahman (BUET)

Topic: GPS Based Autonomous Mars Rover Navigation & On-board Object Detection for URC and Way-point Based Autonomous Mars Rover Navigation & On-board AR Tag Detection for ERC.

• Researcher & Collaborator at Department of ME, BUET

Undergraduate Thesis

Mar 2018 – Apr 2019
Supervisors: Dr. Maglub Al Nur (BUET) and Dr. Muhammad Abir (MIT)

Dhaka, Bangladesh
Topic: Computational Investigation on Pool Boiling IR Images for Segmentation of Dry Spots
Automatically and Evaluating Performance of Traditional Image Processing and Deep Neural
Networks in Quantifying Dry Area Segments.

• Team Leader, Team Octatron

Undergraduate Project Mar 2017 - Feb 2018
Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Musanna Galib (BUET) Dhaka, Bangladesh
Topic: Fire and Flood Fighter Octocopter (UAV) for Extinguishing Fire in Fire Affected Buildings
and Areas, and Distributing Flood Reliefs to people in Flood Affected Zones.

• Researcher & Technical Leader, Team Out of the Box

Microsoft BD Internship Project Jan 2017 - May 2017 Supervisors: Sonia B. Kabir and Ashikur Rahman (Microsoft) Dhaka, Bangladesh Topic: Earlier Screening of Particular Disability in Children Through Mobile Application Using Microsoft Products like Azure Cloud Platform and Bing Maps Server.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

**BUET Mars Rover Robotics Team** Oct 2020 - Present Teaching Assistant at Mars Rover Lab (MRL), BUET Dhaka, Bangladesh • JAXA org. Kibo Astrobee ISS Robot Prog. Challenge Jan 2020 - Present Educator & Instructor of Teams from Bangladesh, STEMX 365 Dhaka, Bangladesh **National Space Carnival & Camp** Sep 2019 - Jun 2020 Instructor & Academic Coordinator for Workshops & Camps Dhaka, Bangladesh Mar 2017 – Apr 2019 **Bangladesh Astronomical Society** *Instructor for Workshops & Seminars* Dhaka, Bangladesh

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Lotus Robotics
 Advisor & Robotics Engineer
 Oct 2021 – Jun 2022
 Newyork, USA

Activities: Worked on Autonomous UGVs for GPS guided delivery missions, Warehouse Security, Lawn Mowing & Floor Scrubbing and UAVs for agriculture and surveying.

Bangladesh Astronomy Research Collaboration (BARC)
 Advisor & Fellow Member
 Activities: Give advice on research activities & how the organization should operate.

• Youthprenuer Network (A Social Welfare Organization)

Head of STEM Education & Development

Activities: Instructed, Organized and Lead Projects, Workshops, Olympiads and Camps in Educational Institutions to Promote STEM Education in Bangladesh.

American Astronomical Society
Country Collaborator & Member
Activities: Celebrated International Astronomical Events in Bangladesh and Reported to Proper AAS Authority for Publishing on their Magazines.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- Kamak Ebadi, Lukas Bernreiter, Harel Biggie, Gavin Catt, Yun Chang, Arghya Chatterjee, Christopher E Denniston, ..., Ali Akbar Agha-mohammadi, Kostas Alexis, Christoffer Hecman, Kasra Khosoussi, Navinda Kottege, Benjamin Morrell, MArco Hutter, Fred Pauling, Francois Pomerleau, Martin Saska, Sebastian Scherer, Roland Siegwart, Jason L Williams, Luca Carlone, "Present and Future of SLAM in Extreme Underground Environments," 2022 Journal of IEEE Transactions on Robotics (TRO).
- Yun Chang, Kamak Ebadi, Christopher E Denniston, Muhammad Fadhil Ginting, Antoni Rosinol, Andrzej Reinke, Matteo Palieri, Jingnan Shi, Arghya Chatterjee, Benjamin Morrell, Ali-akbar Agha-mohammadi, Luca Carlone, "LAMP 2.0: A Robust Multi-Robot SLAM System for Operation in Challenging Large-Scale Underground Environments," 2022 IEEE International Conference on Intelligent Robotics and Systems (IROS).
- Matteo Palieri, Benjamin Morrell, Abhishek Thakur, Kamak Ebadi, Jeremy Nash, Arghya Chatterjee, Christoforos Kanellakis, Luca Carlone, Cataldo Guaragnella, Ali-akbar Agha-mohammadi, "LOCUS: A Multi-Sensor Lidar-Centric Solution for High-Precision Odometry and 3D Mapping in Real-Time," IEEE Robotics & Automation Letters Journal, 2020, vol: 6/2, pp. 421-428.
- Arghya Chatterjee, M. Galib and M. A. R. Sarkar, "Application of Arduino in designing modern electromechanical laboratory," 2017 IEEE International Conference on Power, Control, Signals and Instrumentation Engineering (ICPCSI), Chennai, 2017, pp. 222-225.
- **Arghya Chatterjee**, S. Dutta, P. Sarkar and A. B. M. A. A. Islam, "Obstacle Detector for Blind People with Low Cost (Poster Presentation)," Proceedings of 2017 International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security (NSysS), Dhaka, 2017.

#### **INTERNSHIPS & TRAININGS**

NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL)
 Internship Project: Robustfying Perception Pipeline for DARPA RACER Vehicles

 Microsoft Bangladesh Limited
 Internship Project: Disabling Disability through Microsoft Products
 May 2023 – Present California, USA
 Jan 2017 - May 2017
 Dhaka, Bangladesh

• Khulna Power Company Limited Oct 2018 – Oct 2018 Training: Power Plant Visit & Industrial Attachment (3 weeks) Khulna, Bangladesh

#### SKILL SETS

- **Prg. Language:** Python, C++, Java, C#, Arduino, Java S, HTML, PHP, CSS, & LATEX.
- **Framework & OS:** ROS, ROS2, OpenCV, PCL, Nvidia Isaac SDK, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Caffe, CUDA, OpenGL, Kubernetes, .NET, Django, Linux, Mac, Windows & Android.
- **Software & Tool:** Git, Github, Gitlab, Docker, MIPAR, Solidworks, Ansys, PLC, Blender, Unity & UE 4, Verge3D, Carla Simulator, Microsoft Airsim, Deeplab, OpenPose3D, Meshroom, Meshlab, CloudCompare, Open3D, OpenDroneMap, OpenSpace, Photoshop, Kdenlive & MS Office Family.
- **IDE, Compiler & Text Editor:** CodeBlocks, Microsoft Visual Studio, MATLAB, Atom, Jupiter Notebook, PyCharm, Android Studio, Nodejs, IntelliJ IDEA,VS Code & Notepad++.
- **Cloud Platform:** AWS Compute, AWS RoboMaker & Storage, GCP, Google Colab.
- Hardware: GPS (RTK), IMU, VLP-16 (3D) & RPLidar (2D) LIDAR, Intel Realsense D200 & 400 series RGBD & L515 Lidar Camera, ZED 3D Camera, Microsoft Kinect Camera, Nvidia Jetson & Intel NUC Boards, Arduino & Raspberry PI Boards, Pixhawk, Ardupilot, VESC, BLDC motor, Nvidia AMD GTX Boards & Oculus Rift S VR Headset.
- Language Proficiency: Bangla, English & Hindi.

# AWARDS, HONORS & SCHOLARSHIPS

• **5th Worldwide in Final Round of DARPA SubT Challenge**Awarded to Team CoSTAR of NASA JPL for competing in the final round

Kentucky, USA

Special Grant from ICT Division (Ministry) of BangladeshFeb 2020Awarded to BUET Mars Rover Lab (MRL) for outstanding performance in roboticsDhaka, BD

•	Gold Medalist from Duke of Edinburgh Internation	nai Foundation	Dec 2019
	Awarded for Outstanding Extra-curricular & Service to the Society		London, UK
•	2nd in Asia & 16th Internationally in European Mars Rover Challenge		Sep 2019
	Organized by European Space Foundation (ESF) & Eur	ropean Space Agency (ESA)	Kielce, Poland
•	Special Fund & Grant from BUET Alumni Association Trust		Jul 2019
	Awarded to Team Interplanetar of BUET MRL for com	petition & robotics research	Dhaka, BD
•	Finalist in IEEE SS12 International Project Competition & Maker Fair		Jul 2017
	Organized at SS12: Age of Innovation and Maker Fair	2017	Hyderabad, India
•	1st in National Project Show Competition (Senior Category)		May 2017
	Organized at EEE Day, BUET		Dhaka, BD
•	3rd in Inter University Project Show Competition		Apr 2017
	Organized at Mechanical Festival, BUET		Dhaka, BD
•	1st in National Poster Presentation Competition		Mar 2017
	Organized at Robolution, MIST		Dhaka, BD
•	2nd in Inter University Project Show Competition	1	Nov 2016
	Organized at CSE Day, BUET		Dhaka, BD
•	1st in All Classes (2002 - 2014)		
	• Primary at Elizabeth M Primary School (2002-2006)	• Junior at Khulna BKS Sc	hool (2006-2009)
	<ul> <li>Secondary at Khulna BKS School (2009-2012)</li> </ul>	• H. S. at Khulna Public Co	ollege (2013-2014)
•	Govt. Merit Scholarship from Education Board of Bangladesh (2006 - 2019)		
	<ul><li>Primary Scholarship (2006-2009)</li></ul>	arship (2006-2009) • Junior Scholarship (2010-2012)	
	<ul><li>Secondary Scholarship (2013-2014)</li></ul>	<ul> <li>H. Secondary Scholarship (2015-2019)</li> </ul>	
•	Olympiad Achievements		
	• 1 st in Reg. R. of Science Olympiad'14	• 1 st in Reg. R. of Zoology	Olympiad'14
	• 3 rd in Reg. & 10 th in Nat. R. of Astro-Olympiad'13	• 3 rd in Reg. R. of Math Olympiad'14	

# **CERTIFICATIONS (COURSERA)**

- Machine Learning by Stanford University, Feb 2018.
- **Deep Learning Specialization** (5 course) by Deeplearning.ai, Sept 2018.
- Robotics Specialization (6 course) by University of Pennsylvania (Upenn), Sept 2021.
- Modern Robotics: Mechanics, Planning & Control Specialization by Northwestern Uni, May 2021.
- Control of Mobile Robots by Georgia Institute of Technology, May 2020.
- Image & Video Processing by Duke University, Nov 2018.
- Intro to Satellite Communications by Institut Mines Télécom, May 2019.
- Wireless Communications for Everybody by Yonsei University, Dec 2018.

### **LEADERSHIPS**

Head of STEM Education & Development

• Software **Team Lead** 

• **Technical Lead** of Internship Project

• **President** (Senior Rover Mate)

President

Youthprenuer Network Team Interplanetar, BUET Microsoft BD BUET Rover Scout Group Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET

#### REFERENCES

• Dr. Benjamin Morrell

Perception Team Leader, Team CoSTAR Robotics Technologist, NASA JPL .
Ex. Post Doc Researcher, JPL, Caltech .
Email: benjamin.morrell@jpl.nasa.gov

• Dr. Shehryar Khattak

Perception Team Leader, Team X-RACER Robotics Technologist, NASA JPL. Email: <a href="mailto:skhattak@ipl.nasa.gov">skhattak@ipl.nasa.gov</a>

• Dr. Robert Griffin

PhD. Co-Supervisor Research Professor, Dept. of ISR, UWF. Research Scientist, IHMC. Email: rgriffin@ihmc.org

• Dr. Luca Carlone

Perception Team Supervisor, Team CoSTAR

Professor, Dept. of Aero Astro., MIT.

Email: <a href="mailto:lcarlone@mit.edu">lcarlone@mit.edu</a>